<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Structure on Prototyping Experimental Textiles</title>
    <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Structure on Prototyping Experimental Textiles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Staple Fiber</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/staple-fiber/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/staple-fiber/</guid>
      <description>Staple Fiber # Image: Wool fiber. Credit: Rob / CC BY
A fiber is one of primary building blocks of textiles, it describe a material with a high length to width ratio. A staple fiber has a limited length while filaments have unlimited length. Staple fibers are categorized into categories based on their source and chemical properties:
Natural fibers are those that come from animals and plants. The size and length of staple fiber thus depends on what can be grown and harvested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filament</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/filament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/filament/</guid>
      <description>Filament # Image Caption: Bundles of silk filament. National Archives and Records Administration / Public domain
A filament is a fiber of unlimited or very long length. Filaments are typically produced through extrusion, are of uniform length and quality. Silk is said to be a natural filament because it can be harvested in single lengths that are very long. Other common filaments include copper magnet wire, nylon, and rayon. Because of their uniform structure, they can often be very light and strong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roving and Top</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/roving-and-top/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/roving-and-top/</guid>
      <description>Roving and Top # Image Caption: Roving (the form shown on the right) pictured alongside singles and spun yarn on a drop spindle. Credit: Lisa Dusseault on Flickr
Roving and or Top describe fibers that have been given and initial structure to hold them together, but have not yet been given any twist. These are produced by processes of combing or carding individual fibers into into a common direction prior to spinning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singles</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/singles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/singles/</guid>
      <description>Singles # singles describes the first structure that emerges after roving or top are given spin. Most yarns are often made from several strands of singles.
Singles are produced when roving or top are twisted in the process of spinning, turning into a longer yarn-like structure. Most yarns are created through one or more singles joined together, in a process called plying which adds additional structure and texture to yarn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plied Yarn</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/plied-yarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/plied-yarn/</guid>
      <description>Plied Yarn # 2-ply yarn. If you look closely, you can see the two individual singles strands twisted together. Image Credit: Natalia Wilson on Flickr.
The yarn or thread that you purchase for projects just as knitting, sewing or weaving is plied meaning that it has been created through a process of plying several singles yarns and/or filaments together.
A 2-ply yarn is made of 2 singles, a 3-ply is made of three singles and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yarn / Thread</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/yarn-thread/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/yarn-thread/</guid>
      <description>Yarn / Thread # The terms yarn and thread typically describe any material that is long and thin. However, they are not indicative of a particular structure.
A thread describes a very thin yarn, so &amp;ldquo;yarn&amp;rdquo; is the broader term. Both threads and yarns can take the form of filament, singles, plied yarn, core-spun yarn, or braids.
At times you might see yarns described as &amp;ldquo;knitting&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;weaving&amp;rdquo; yarns, but this only indicates the kind of application the designer envisioned for the yarn and likely a set of properties it might have (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knit</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/knit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/knit/</guid>
      <description>Knit # __A knit is a textile structure created by arranging material (most often plied yarn and filaments) into a series of interconnecting loops. These interconnecting loops can create a flat-(ish) textile with the ability to stretch in all directions as well as tubular or flat circular structures that strength along their length and width. The amount of stretch for a given knit depends on the materials, density, and stitches used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Woven</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/non-woven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/non-woven/</guid>
      <description>Non-Woven # Non-wovens describe a class of textile structures that are not created through knitting or weaving. In most cases, they describe structures that bi-pass the processing of fiber into yarn. Instead, non-wovens are textile-like materials that are created by other processes of extruding (e.g. chainmail or 3D printed textiles), growing (such as leather or kombucha), felting, a process by which individual fibers are tangled so much as to form a durable surface or structure, or electrospinning, where fibers are bonded into a fabric through electrical charge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Woven</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/woven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/woven/</guid>
      <description>Woven # A woven textile structure is created by interlacing material (most often plied yarn and filaments) in two directions: the warp (threads running along the length), and weft (threads running along the width). These structures are created by stretching or &amp;ldquo;warping&amp;rdquo; a set of parallel yarns (or radical yarns in circular weaving), and then interweaving the weft yarns in a perpendicular direction to bind the textile together. The specific patterning of &amp;ldquo;overs&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;unders&amp;rdquo; gives the woven textile different thicknesses, ability to sheer, and durability, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/braid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/braid/</guid>
      <description>Braid # a close up of a braided cord. nylon roving was directly braided into this structure.
A braid is a structure that is created by interlacing singles, plied yarns and/or filaments in a flat, but more often, tubular structure. The most noticeable difference between a plied structure and a braided one is that the braid requires materials to travel in two directions around a center point. A tubular braid is a hollow structure and can be left hollow for particular applications and has particularly good mechanical properties for artificial muscles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/core-spun-yarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/core-spun-yarn/</guid>
      <description>Core Spun Yarn # Core spun yarns describe a multi-layered yarn structure where fiber is spun around a single continuous filament in the core. This is a common technique for creating conductive yarns. The internal material is referred to as the core, and the outer is referred to as the sheath. There is a seemingly endless combination and set of techniques for constructing core spun yarns, which you can find here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/textile-friendly-object/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/textile-friendly-object/</guid>
      <description>Textile Friendly Object # While we have covered a series of possible structure that accumulate to build textiles, there are an almost infinite amount of variations and things that can be added that change the quality of a textile that we did not cover.
Any long thing material (especially pliable) material can be used as a textile material and integrated into braids, knits, and wovens. This includes materials like rubber tubing, paper strips, chainlink, materials that can be rolled or torn into long lengths like old blankets and rags, or even vines.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
