<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Resources on Prototyping Experimental Textiles</title>
    <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Resources on Prototyping Experimental Textiles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/collections-of-techniques-and-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/collections-of-techniques-and-examples/</guid>
      <description>Collections of Techniques and Examples # Kobakant: How to Get What you Want # a collection of how to&amp;rsquo;s, resources, and inspirations for all kinds of soft making. Compiled from examples created by Hannah Perner Wilson and Mika Satomi. https://www.kobakant.at/DIY/
Stitching Worlds # Stitching Worlds &amp;ldquo;connects the shared artistic research territory between arts, design, open culture, digital fabrication, information technology and electronics to the engineering and scientific methodologies of textile technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/how-to-weave/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/how-to-weave/</guid>
      <description>How to Weave on Floor Loom # Anatomy # Below is the anatomy of a floor loom.
The loom consists of several parts. More details about each part can be found in the key terms section.
Basic Mechanics # [1] There are multiple treadles on the loom. There are multiple shafts on the loom.
[2] The treadles can be tied up to as many shafts as the weaver desires. The tie up connects the shaft to the treadles so that the weaver can control which warp is raised and lowered</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/suppliers-of-prepared-thread-yarn-and-filament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/suppliers-of-prepared-thread-yarn-and-filament/</guid>
      <description>Suppliers of Prepared Thread, Yarn and Filament # The kinds of yarns that we have ordered and have in the lab recently come from various suppliers, but have also come with quite of lot of improvisation and collaborating with European friends in order to order (including some email translations, etc.). You&amp;rsquo;ll also notice that some suppliers use the language of yarn to describe their yarns (ply, denier, etc) while others describe them more like wires (diameter or AWG).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
