<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prototyping Experimental Textiles</title>
    <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Prototyping Experimental Textiles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Materials</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/comparing-materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/comparing-materials/</guid>
      <description>Comparing Materials # In some projects, you may want to select fibers based on the properties you need and its useful to be able to look at them side by side and see which you might prefer. To help this, we have attempted to put information about each fiber in a common space. These, however, are incredibly general as some measurements (e.g. resistivity) will vary greatly on the specific preparation of the material for use in a textile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Contribute</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/contribute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/contribute/</guid>
      <description>How to Contribute # It is our intention for this book to become a resource that an entire community can contribute towards. Hoping this will be an open source book, forked, edited, and added to by others.
If you would like to contribute to the book, visit the GitHub repository for the project at: https://github.com/UnstableDesign/PrototypingSmartTextiles
If you are comfortable with GitHub and the command line interface, you can follow these instructions to make changes and submit pull requests to the organizers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Staple Fiber</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/staple-fiber/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/staple-fiber/</guid>
      <description>Staple Fiber # Image: Wool fiber. Credit: Rob / CC BY
A fiber is one of primary building blocks of textiles, it describe a material with a high length to width ratio. A staple fiber has a limited length while filaments have unlimited length. Staple fibers are categorized into categories based on their source and chemical properties:
Natural fibers are those that come from animals and plants. The size and length of staple fiber thus depends on what can be grown and harvested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filament</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/filament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/filament/</guid>
      <description>Filament # Image Caption: Bundles of silk filament. National Archives and Records Administration / Public domain
A filament is a fiber of unlimited or very long length. Filaments are typically produced through extrusion, are of uniform length and quality. Silk is said to be a natural filament because it can be harvested in single lengths that are very long. Other common filaments include copper magnet wire, nylon, and rayon. Because of their uniform structure, they can often be very light and strong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protein</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/protein-fibers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/protein-fibers/</guid>
      <description>Protein Fibers # Wool # Wool fiber is harvested from animals, such as sheep, goats and alpaca, and can be obtained in many different grades that make it softer, more brash, etc. for different purposes. When the word &amp;ldquo;wool&amp;rdquo; is used, it is typically referring to sheeps wool. Typically, wools with shorter and finer staple lengths (like cashmere or merino) are carded into woolen yarns for exceptional softness. Longer staple fibers are used for more durable applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roving and Top</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/roving-and-top/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/roving-and-top/</guid>
      <description>Roving and Top # Image Caption: Roving (the form shown on the right) pictured alongside singles and spun yarn on a drop spindle. Credit: Lisa Dusseault on Flickr
Roving and or Top describe fibers that have been given and initial structure to hold them together, but have not yet been given any twist. These are produced by processes of combing or carding individual fibers into into a common direction prior to spinning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Traces</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/traces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/traces/</guid>
      <description>Traces # A trace is a conductive material that carries electricity from one location in your circuit to another. In traditional electronics, your traces are usually insulated wires with uninsulated tips that you plug into a breadboard or solder to a controller.
In soft electronics traces can be created from a single thread traveling through a material, a conductive fabric or paint fused to the surface of a fabric or a single thread of material integrated into a knit or woven fabric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cellulose</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/cellulose-fibers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/cellulose-fibers/</guid>
      <description>Cellulose Based # Cellulose fibers are obtained from plants such as cotton, flax (linen), bamboo, and hemp.
Cotton # Cotton is the most commonly used material in garments. This is partly because it is soft and breathable but also because it is stronger when it is wet, making it easy to wash in conventional washing machine. Different cottons have different qualities and grades, but they are a bit more consistent between varieties than different kinds of wool, for instance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connections</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/connections/</guid>
      <description>Connections # Once you have made your traces, you must then find ways to connect different &amp;ldquo;components&amp;rdquo; together. Good connections should be tight, robust and tidy, making sure that they don&amp;rsquo;t break or short your circuit unexpectedly.
There are two primary modes of connecting: soft-to-soft, where both things being connected are flexible and stretchable, or soft-to-hard where you are connecting a soft material to a rigid material (e.g. a thread to an Arduino).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resistors</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/resistors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/resistors/</guid>
      <description>Resistors # Every conductive material imposes a certain amount of resistance per unit length. The amount of resistance can be measured by a multimeter and depends on a number of factors such as temperature, width, material, etc. A resistor, in traditional electronics, is used to limit the voltage provided to a particular part of your circuit (because Voltage = current * resistance).
Making Resistors with Conductive Thread # In traditional electronics, you typically purchase resistors of set values that you need.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singles</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/singles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/singles/</guid>
      <description>Singles # singles describes the first structure that emerges after roving or top are given spin. Most yarns are often made from several strands of singles.
Singles are produced when roving or top are twisted in the process of spinning, turning into a longer yarn-like structure. Most yarns are created through one or more singles joined together, in a process called plying which adds additional structure and texture to yarn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plied Yarn</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/plied-yarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/plied-yarn/</guid>
      <description>Plied Yarn # 2-ply yarn. If you look closely, you can see the two individual singles strands twisted together. Image Credit: Natalia Wilson on Flickr.
The yarn or thread that you purchase for projects just as knitting, sewing or weaving is plied meaning that it has been created through a process of plying several singles yarns and/or filaments together.
A 2-ply yarn is made of 2 singles, a 3-ply is made of three singles and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resistive Sensing</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/resistive-sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/resistive-sensors/</guid>
      <description>Resistive Sensors # Resistive sensors describe a class of sensors who work because of changes in their resistance. These resistance changes often come from a structural change in the materials. Resistive sensing works many times because electricity will always follow the shortest path from power to ground (+ to -). Thus, if a structural change changes the path electricity takes, the measure of resistance will change proportional to the length of the path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/synthetic-fibers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/synthetic-fibers/</guid>
      <description>Synthetic Fibers # Synthetic fibers are made from chemical solutions, such a polymer solutions, that are extruded and cured or otherwise formed into filaments. Sometimes these are cut to produce staple fibers. Synthetic fibers are engineered to provide interesting properties (such as piezoelectric effects) and/or to mimic the properties of existing materials at a lower cost, such as the case of nylon, which was originally branded as &amp;ldquo;artificial silk.&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yarn / Thread</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/yarn-thread/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/yarn-thread/</guid>
      <description>Yarn / Thread # The terms yarn and thread typically describe any material that is long and thin. However, they are not indicative of a particular structure.
A thread describes a very thin yarn, so &amp;ldquo;yarn&amp;rdquo; is the broader term. Both threads and yarns can take the form of filament, singles, plied yarn, core-spun yarn, or braids.
At times you might see yarns described as &amp;ldquo;knitting&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;weaving&amp;rdquo; yarns, but this only indicates the kind of application the designer envisioned for the yarn and likely a set of properties it might have (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insulation</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/insulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/insulation/</guid>
      <description>Insulation # Insulation is a method for preventing the flow of electricity to areas neighboring your traces. Some soft sensor and actuator structures rely on traces being insulated from one and other, others don&amp;rsquo;t. In some cases, you might also find that your materials already come insulated. In others, you need to provide insulation yourself. You can test if your material is insulated or not by connecting a multimeter across a length of conductive string and seeing and checking for a connection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnets</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/electromagnet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/electromagnet/</guid>
      <description>Electromagnets # Electromagnets describe magnetic feilds that are created by the flow of electricity through wires. Electromagnetism is at the root of many microphones and speakers as coils induce the attaction or repulsion of a magnet attached to a drum like membrane that pushes air back and forth to make sound. Many motors are also controlled by electromangets that push and pull a central shaft around a central point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physical State Change</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/physical-state-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/physical-state-change/</guid>
      <description>In progress!
Physical State Change # Shape Change # https://parametrichouse.com/responsive-textiles/
pneumatics / jamming
artificial muscles
Lets start with a McKibben artificial muscle which consists of a rope that is braided around a ****hollow tube. When you pressurize the fluid (air or water) in the tube, the braided structure amplifies the movement. In most DIY examples, we see these made by simply buying a pre-made braided hollow cord and shoving a hollow tube down the center of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Knit</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/knit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/knit/</guid>
      <description>Knit # __A knit is a textile structure created by arranging material (most often plied yarn and filaments) into a series of interconnecting loops. These interconnecting loops can create a flat-(ish) textile with the ability to stretch in all directions as well as tubular or flat circular structures that strength along their length and width. The amount of stretch for a given knit depends on the materials, density, and stitches used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Woven</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/non-woven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/non-woven/</guid>
      <description>Non-Woven # Non-wovens describe a class of textile structures that are not created through knitting or weaving. In most cases, they describe structures that bi-pass the processing of fiber into yarn. Instead, non-wovens are textile-like materials that are created by other processes of extruding (e.g. chainmail or 3D printed textiles), growing (such as leather or kombucha), felting, a process by which individual fibers are tangled so much as to form a durable surface or structure, or electrospinning, where fibers are bonded into a fabric through electrical charge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Woven</title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/woven/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/woven/</guid>
      <description>Woven # A woven textile structure is created by interlacing material (most often plied yarn and filaments) in two directions: the warp (threads running along the length), and weft (threads running along the width). These structures are created by stretching or &amp;ldquo;warping&amp;rdquo; a set of parallel yarns (or radical yarns in circular weaving), and then interweaving the weft yarns in a perpendicular direction to bind the textile together. The specific patterning of &amp;ldquo;overs&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;unders&amp;rdquo; gives the woven textile different thicknesses, ability to sheer, and durability, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/capacitors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/dynamics/capacitors/</guid>
      <description>Capacitors # knitted capacitors (knitted radio)
woven capacitors
**** # **** # How does capacitive sensing work
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bhspPkxOMxs
A deeper explanation of what capacitance is
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QItuf6lNvmI
Swept Frequency Capacitive Sensing
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E4tYpXVTjxA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/metallic-fibers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/materials/metallic-fibers/</guid>
      <description>Metallic Fibers # Metallic fibers are those that conduct electricity and are often blended, as fibers or filaments with non-conductive fibers to make workable yarn.
The table below represents the resistivity of metallic yarns in comparison to other natural and synthetic fibers. The metallic fibers numbers are consistently measured where the other numbers should be taken with a VERY BIG grain of salt as I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to find consistent measurements across fibers so they represent whatever I could find anywhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/bonding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/bonding/</guid>
      <description>Bonding / Laser Welding # Bonding is process of using heat or other adhesives to fuse two layers of material or multiple structures together. It works though the magic of fusible interfacings, fabric materials that contain adhesives that &amp;ldquo;glue&amp;rdquo; fabrics together when heated. Basically, conductive fabrics and interfacing can be cut in the same patterns and fused, to create functional systems and circuits such as these examples below. A key point to make, highlighted in the work below, is to ensure that your interfacing has an open-enough mesh for any conductive layers to make contact with one another, if that is the property you are looking for</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/braiding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/braiding/</guid>
      <description>Braiding # Braiding is a technique that uses coils multiple strands, in different twist directions around a solid or hollow core. Industrial braiding uses a machine called a &amp;ldquo;maypole machine&amp;rdquo; that is utterly fascinating to watch. Braiding is often used for creating sheaths around a core. What is nice about braiding is you can have a core that is a completely different material than the sheath without having to wrestle with too many different issues in tensioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/coating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/coating/</guid>
      <description>Coating / Painting / Printing # A method for adding some material or texture onto a material structure. Often by immersing and dying in a bath or spraying. Painting can be seen as a process of coating, whereby pigments are applied to the surface of the structure. Other processes of coating include mercerization, whereby chemical processes are applied to change the chemical properties of the material in the structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/combing-and-carding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/combing-and-carding/</guid>
      <description>Combing and Carding # Carding yarns arranges the fibers in multiple directions and is referred to as a &amp;ldquo;woolen&amp;rdquo; preparation of fibers. Carding fibers produces roving. Fibers of all different lengths are kept in this process. The goal of carding is to build up enough of a &amp;ldquo;mesh&amp;rdquo; of fibers that they hold together. These meshes, and the process, yields more airy, fluffy and soft yarns. Bundles of woolen fibers are most often called &amp;ldquo;roving&amp;rdquo; but you different preparations go by names batts, rolags, fauxlags, puin, cloud, and wool locks, each of which offers, as you expect, its own set of unique qualities to the fibers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/dying-resists/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/dying-resists/</guid>
      <description>Dying / Resists # Dying is a surface application for structures that imbues them with particular color patterns and characteristics. Dying requires a chemical bond to form between a fiber and the dye compound. This chemical bond is what makes something a dye, rather than a paint, which is made from pigment and is attached to the surface of a material via a medium. Dyes typically produce a softer hand than painted yarns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/electroplating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/electroplating/</guid>
      <description>Electroplating # Most conductive yarns and threads are created by electroplating polymer materials such as nylon. Electroplating is a process of using electrically charged solutions to bound metallic substances to the surface of a structure. There are rules about which materials will plate to others (somewhere?), but the brave souls of YouTube have tried to show us how to do electroplating at home with household materials.
DIY Silver Electroplating</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/electrospinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/electrospinning/</guid>
      <description> Electrospinning # </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/embroidery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/embroidery/</guid>
      <description>Embroidery # embroidery is a surface application technique applied to existing fabrics. It is similar to and often used in conjunction with sewing, bit focuses much more on the application of threads to the surface of a fabric for decorative and/or functional purposes.
Structure Ability to be Emboiderd or Embroidered Upon by Hand By Machine Raw Fiber no no Filament yes? (perhaps through laying? or by hand. no? Roving &amp;amp; Top no?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/etching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/etching/</guid>
      <description>Etching # Etching # Salt and Vinegar Etching
Hydrogren Peroxide Etching</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/extruding-3d-printing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/extruding-3d-printing/</guid>
      <description>Extruding / 3D Printing # Extruding # A second common process uses processes of extrusion. In these cases, materials are processed into a liquid like goo (think play-doh) and pressed through narrow openings named after a spider&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;spinneret.&amp;rdquo; The single streams of material emerging from the spinneret are either spun directly into fiber or deposited into liquid chemical baths as part of their structural formation. Often, extruding gives rise to filaments, where long continuous fibers are created.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/felting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/felting/</guid>
      <description>Felting # a process of creating non-wovens that directly tangles fibers to create a fabric.
Needle Felting # Needle felting binds fibers to themselves or to a textile surface through the stabbing or a barbed needle repeatedly through the fabric. This technique can be used for creating surfaces as well as shapes, can create objects entirely out of fibers and/or to add texture/interactivity to the surface of a fabric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/growing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/growing/</guid>
      <description>Growing # a process of doping a material or guiding a material as it grows over time. A typical process for non-woven preparations.
Growing Crystals:
http://www.rachelfreire.com/etextile-crystallography
Structure Ability to be Grown Ability to be initegrated into Growth Processes or Grown Upon? Raw Fiber sure yes? Filament yes yes? Roving &amp;amp; Top no, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you could directly grow rowing hummm Singles no, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you could directly grow singles, though something similar could be yes?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/knitting/hand-knitting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/knitting/hand-knitting/</guid>
      <description>Hand Knitting # Hand knitting takes place with knitting needles, manipulated by the hands. This technique allows for playful discovery of stitches and structures and, depending on the kind of needle, can be used to knit surfaces, tubes, or volumes. The material, gauge, stitch, and needle size all shift the texture of the knit itself, giving way to more stretchy, bully, light, or rigid textures. Textures in handknitting can change at any point in the process across the surface by changing the stitch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/knitting/machine-knitting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/knitting/machine-knitting/</guid>
      <description>Machine Knitting # There are two main types of knitting machines that can used for tabletop knitting. These machines are made possible through &amp;ldquo;latchhook needles.&amp;rdquo; A flat bed machine, comes in two &amp;lsquo;gauges&amp;rsquo;, standard and chunky. The gauge of the machine refers to the spacing between the needles in the bed of the machine, which allows for different size yarns to run through the machine. These machines can be programmed electronically, or via punchcard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/paper-making/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/paper-making/</guid>
      <description>Paper-Making # a process for preparing non-woven fabric (like paper) by creating a solution of fibers in a pulp and drying them in sheets using a mesh like fabric. The videos below show techniques for creating paper from other paper as well as from plant materials:
Techniques for Creating Paper # Making Paper from recycling other paper
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QxyKvyGC5GA
Handmade Paper from Grass
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EsiKZx-KbBI
Stinging Nettle Paper
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1VJMR4orW28
Sekishu-Banshi
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p2WXBZQ3S18</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/pleating/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/pleating/</guid>
      <description> Pleating # </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/ad-hoc-plying/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/ad-hoc-plying/</guid>
      <description> Ad Hoc Plying # You can also ply by hand by twisting any long and durable material in your hands, in one direction, folding it, and gently encourage its natural inclination to spin in the other direction.
Online Resources # A DIY Conductive Thread / Rope Machine - Lynne Bruning Demonstration of Plying 6 Strands into Rope on a Large Scale. Text Resources
TBD </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/plying-on-a-spinning-wheel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/plying-on-a-spinning-wheel/</guid>
      <description>Plying on a Spinning Wheel # A spinning wheel is the most common method of plying long lengths of yarn by craft spinners, as shown in this tutorial
Online Resources
****Making a 2-Ply Yarn on a Spinning Wheel 3 Techniques for Plying Handspun Yarn on an E-Spinner **** Text Resources # Yarnitecture: A Knitter&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Spinning: Building Exactly the Yarn You Want
Book by Jillian Moreno</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/plying-with-a-drop-spindle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/plying-with-a-drop-spindle/</guid>
      <description> Plying with a Drop Spindle # A drop spindle can also works for plying as shown in this demonstration of creating a 2x2 ply yarn.
Online Resources # Plying Custom Conductive/Color-Changing Yarn, ****Anne-Marie Lavigne DIY Drop Spindle Creativebug Studios**** </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/plying-with-a-rope-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/plying/plying-with-a-rope-machine/</guid>
      <description> Plying with a Rope Machine # rope making machines offer a simple assembly for creating multi-strand plys and ropes.
Online Resources # Another DIY setup using a power drill How to use a Schacht Incredible Rope Machine Text Resources
TBD </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/sewing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/sewing/</guid>
      <description>Sewing # Hand Sewing
Running Stitch
Back Stitch
Whip Stitch
Blanket Stitch</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/sewing/hand-sewing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/sewing/hand-sewing/</guid>
      <description>Hand Sewing # While we offer a few different techniques below, there are excellent tutorials focused on sewing circuits. For instance, Spark Fun offers a great intro to Sewing to a Lilypad Arduino. Below, we offer a more generalized introduction with a focus on the different stitches you might choose to use and how they can be useful within e-textiles. If you are interested in a broader set of techniques, such as pleating or sewing patterns, I enjoyed the resources provided by Colleen G Lea on the Fashion Sewing YouTube Channel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/sewing/machine-sewing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/sewing/machine-sewing/</guid>
      <description>Machine Sewing # There are various kind of machine sewing, each one used for different applications. Below, we&amp;rsquo;ll just focus on conventional sewing machines (as opposed to serger, cover-stitch, or embroidery machines)
Conventional Sewing Machines # A conventional sewing machine typically has one top stitching thread (pulled from on top of the machine) and one bobbin (used to secure the backside of the fabric). The two threads work together to find your fabrics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/spinning/drop-spindle-spinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/spinning/drop-spindle-spinning/</guid>
      <description>Drop Spindle Spinning # An accessible method of spinning can be accomplished using a drop spindle. A drop spindle is a modified top that one manually spins in order to add twist to the fiber. This is an ancient practice that still largely resembles its process from 20,000 years ago. For those interested in how these techniques varied in medieval times by region, you may enjoy this demonstration of technique.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/spinning/spinning-wheel-spinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/spinning/spinning-wheel-spinning/</guid>
      <description>Spinning Wheel Spinning # The most common method of spinning requires a spinning wheel (yes, the machine of fairy tale lore), which requires a substantial amount of technique and know how to use it effectively. A spinning wheel requires the spinner to use their feet to spin the wheel at an even pace and both their hands to draw the fibers into the wheel. It is faster and produces higher quality yarn than the other techniques.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/weaving/on-a-frame-loom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/weaving/on-a-frame-loom/</guid>
      <description>Frame Loom Weaving # As you might expect, hand threading a yarn over and under every row can be tedious, which has given rise to the development of horizontal looms with heddles, or, contraptions that lift the warps for you. The heddles lift the yarn, and the weaver throws the yarn through the opening, or shed, lowers the heddles and beats the row they just laid to meet the fabric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/weaving/on-a-tapestry-loom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/weaving/on-a-tapestry-loom/</guid>
      <description>Tapestry Loom Weaving # Weaving on a Tapestry Loom # Tapestry looms are typically frames that allow for yarns to be stretched across their length, and in a fixed length. A weaver can freely weave in and out of the yarns creating more freeform structures and pushing down yarns with a comb. Tapestry looms (and the resulting tapestries) can range in size. This video shows an example of tapestry weaving on a large loom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/weaving/on-an-industrial-jacquard-loom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/process/weaving/on-an-industrial-jacquard-loom/</guid>
      <description>Industrial/Jacquard Loom Weaving # Jacquard Looms # A jacquard-style loom is one where every heddle can be individually controlled. Originally, they were selected by punch cards (which inspired the earliest forms of computing) and today, they are computer controlled with small motors, electromagnets, and or pneumatics. Jacquard style looms fix the position of each heddle, so they typically have a set density they will weave. Jacquard style looms are best for creating non-repeating patterns and more complex woven structures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/quickstart/thermochromics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/quickstart/thermochromics/</guid>
      <description>Programmable Color Changing Fabric # This activities focuses on the creation of a programmable color changing yarn, which can then be knit, woven, or otherwise combined into a programmable color changing fabric.
How Does it Work? # This project leverages thermochromism, the quality of paritcular pigments or dyes to change from a color to transparent above a specified temperature. Specifically, heat causes the chemical structure of the pigments to change, leading our eye to percieve them as either a solid color or transparent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/collections-of-techniques-and-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/collections-of-techniques-and-examples/</guid>
      <description>Collections of Techniques and Examples # Kobakant: How to Get What you Want # a collection of how to&amp;rsquo;s, resources, and inspirations for all kinds of soft making. Compiled from examples created by Hannah Perner Wilson and Mika Satomi. https://www.kobakant.at/DIY/
Stitching Worlds # Stitching Worlds &amp;ldquo;connects the shared artistic research territory between arts, design, open culture, digital fabrication, information technology and electronics to the engineering and scientific methodologies of textile technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/how-to-weave/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/how-to-weave/</guid>
      <description>How to Weave on Floor Loom # Anatomy # Below is the anatomy of a floor loom.
The loom consists of several parts. More details about each part can be found in the key terms section.
Basic Mechanics # [1] There are multiple treadles on the loom. There are multiple shafts on the loom.
[2] The treadles can be tied up to as many shafts as the weaver desires. The tie up connects the shaft to the treadles so that the weaver can control which warp is raised and lowered</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/suppliers-of-prepared-thread-yarn-and-filament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/resources/suppliers-of-prepared-thread-yarn-and-filament/</guid>
      <description>Suppliers of Prepared Thread, Yarn and Filament # The kinds of yarns that we have ordered and have in the lab recently come from various suppliers, but have also come with quite of lot of improvisation and collaborating with European friends in order to order (including some email translations, etc.). You&amp;rsquo;ll also notice that some suppliers use the language of yarn to describe their yarns (ply, denier, etc) while others describe them more like wires (diameter or AWG).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/braid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/braid/</guid>
      <description>Braid # a close up of a braided cord. nylon roving was directly braided into this structure.
A braid is a structure that is created by interlacing singles, plied yarns and/or filaments in a flat, but more often, tubular structure. The most noticeable difference between a plied structure and a braided one is that the braid requires materials to travel in two directions around a center point. A tubular braid is a hollow structure and can be left hollow for particular applications and has particularly good mechanical properties for artificial muscles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/core-spun-yarn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/core-spun-yarn/</guid>
      <description>Core Spun Yarn # Core spun yarns describe a multi-layered yarn structure where fiber is spun around a single continuous filament in the core. This is a common technique for creating conductive yarns. The internal material is referred to as the core, and the outer is referred to as the sheath. There is a seemingly endless combination and set of techniques for constructing core spun yarns, which you can find here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/textile-friendly-object/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://unstable.design/books/prototyping-experimental-textiles/docs/structure/textile-friendly-object/</guid>
      <description>Textile Friendly Object # While we have covered a series of possible structure that accumulate to build textiles, there are an almost infinite amount of variations and things that can be added that change the quality of a textile that we did not cover.
Any long thing material (especially pliable) material can be used as a textile material and integrated into braids, knits, and wovens. This includes materials like rubber tubing, paper strips, chainlink, materials that can be rolled or torn into long lengths like old blankets and rags, or even vines.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
